Preliminary Inventory to the Stéphane Lauzanne Papers, 1898-1954
Hoover Institution Archives
Stéphane Lauzanne Papers,
1898-1954
67010
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 9 oversize boxes (7.1 linear feet)
Writings, transcripts of radio broadcasts, and clippings, relating to French politics and foreign policy, international relations, and the Vichy regime in France during World War II.
Lauzanne, Stéphane, 1874-
Access
Collection open for research.
Scope and Contents note
Writings, transcripts of radio broadcasts, and clippings, relating to French politics and foreign policy, international relations, and the Vichy regime in France during World War II.
Biographical/Historical note
Editor, Le Matin (Paris), 1920-1940.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1967.
France--Foreign relations--1914-1940.; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; France--Politics and government--1914-1940.; France.; Journalists.; Le Matin.; World politics.; World War, 1939-1945--Collaborationists.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Various file folders, subjects designated.
  - Press Conferences, Radio Paris., 31 July - 9 June, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Les hommes d'Europe contre la bête soviétique. (Box 1)
    - Orage sur le Pacifique. (Box 1)
    - La tyrannie des mers. (Box 1)
    - Les étranges variations de M. Roosevelt. (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt - La Guerre. (Box 1)
    - L'anniversaire de Staline. (Box 1)
    - L'Archipel aux sept mille iles. (Box 1)
    - Radio Paris, le, 20, Nov. 1942. (Box 1)
    - Les "Libérateurs" américains s'abattent sur l'Afrique du Nord. (Box 1)
    - Une page déchiré de civilisation française. (Box 1)
    - L'Angleterre candidate à l'Assassinat de Darlan. (Box 1)
    - La France vaincu se battra jusqu'au bout contre le communisme. (Box 1)
    - Les impostures de Roosevelt. (Box 1)
    - L'enterrement du Komintern ou le mort vivant. (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt, coupable no. l de guerre. (Box 1)
    - L'Angleterre prise entre deux jeux. (Box 1)
    - L'explosion du Bolchevik Wells. (Box 1)
    - Un pays ne meurt pas, s'il garde sa force spirituelle. (Box 1)
    - L'Europe n'a qu'un choix: ou s'unir ou mourir! (Box 1)
    - Il y a 40 ans, mourait Paul Krüger. (Box 1)
    - Questions to Stephane Lauzanne by??, presented by Radio Paris (Box 1)
    - pour l'Amérique. (Box 1)
    - Tous les papes contre le communism. (Box 1)
  - "Actualités," articles written for Actualités in the year, 1926. (Box 1)
  - Moitié de Conférence inutile (?). (Box 1)
  - Notes on the events of the march of the Germans into Angers/France in 1940; includes several issues of Le Matin, and one issue Appel Collection et numéros divers du "Petit Courrier" du Matin a Angers., (dated 29. mai 1941). (Box 1)
  - Articles not published. (Box 1)
    - Title: Une force perdue: M. Joseph Caillaux. (Box 1)
    - Title: Guillaume II - La Guerre, (1914-1918). (Box 1)
    - Clippings: Nécrologie de Guillaume II. (Box 1)
  - Lyautey l'africain. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    3 articles Echo (handwritten manuscripts).
  - Rapports mensuels de Juillet (nos. 1 - 26) pour La Mission de Presse et d'Information aux Etats Unis., 1917 á Oct. 1918 (Box 1)
  - La Légion étrange. (Box 2)
  - La République des Soviets et la République Française, (1930). (Box 2)
  - Il y a un siècle.... le ruée vers l'or en Californie, (1949). (Box 2)
  - Une visite à Paris du Tzar Pierre-le-Grand, (1949). (Box 2)
  - Fighting France (Conference held in USA, 1917). (Box 2)
  - Civilisation Française et Civilisation Americaine (Conference in Boston held in, 1917?). (Box 2)
  - La France d'avant la guerre (Conference held in Montréal?) (Box 2)
  - La France d'aujourdhhui - Une famille française en (Conference held for Rumania)., 1914 (Box 2)
  - Au chevet de la Turquie. (Box 2)
  - Le déclin de l'Amérique. (Box 2)
  - L'Europe en Guerre et l'amitié américaine. (Box 2)
  - Le Détraquement de l'Amérique (Conference held in, 1940 and 1942) (Box 2)
  - "Souvenez-vous..." (Conference held in USA, [1917?]). (Box 2)
  - La Société des Nations doit-elle être une cour ou un club?, (n.d.) (Box 2)
  - M. Hearst: Dossier de l'affaire Hearst comme agent de l'Allemagne, son rôle pendant la guerre. (Box 2)
    - Copy of letter to Maurice Léon de M. W. R. Hearst Rapports., (July 10, 1927) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence between M. Léon and Lauzanne. (Box 2)
    - Address by James M. Beck: "The enemy within our gates" (held on, Nov. 2, 1917). (Box 2)
    - Letter to André Tardieu. (Box 2)
    - Letter M. Leon a Lauzanne. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence of the General Manager of International News Service to Lauzanne on, July 17, 1918. (Box 2)
  - Speeches et Allocutions en Amérique, (1917-1918). (Box 2)
    4 speeches (no titles).
    Fragments of speeches and documents for speeches.
    Speech: Les Béquilles de la Paix (20. p.).
  - Conférence réligieuses et historiques, faites à Toiras, (1948/49/50) (Box 2)
    (has table of contents of 13 speeches, but contains only fragments) 2 complete speeches.
  - American Ambassadors by Stephane Lauzanne (article). (Box 2)
  - Conference held in USA: "La Femme française pendant la Guerre" (Box 2)
  - Conference: "L'Angleterre, cette ile" (held in Paris in, 1938). (Box 2)
  - L'élection présidentielle américaine de (clippings)., 1952 (Box 2)
  - Les 17 Ministres de la IV République Française ( Aurore). (Box 2)
  - Conference: "L'Ame americaine," held in Brussels in, 1920 and 1937. (Box 2)
  - Conference held in USA in English and in French: "Une heure dans une tranchée de Verdun." (Box 2)
  - Dossier Roosevelt and Lindbergh: (Box 2)
    - Les Etats Unis et la Guerre. (Box 2)
      (Contains clippings, letter to Sapene from Jan. 18, 1923.)
    - Bulletin published by Nouvelles Cont. on the German White Book., 1943 (Box 2)
    - Articles: "L'Affamement de l'Europe" (Box 2)
    - "Un tre admirable: Charles Lindbergh" (Box 2)
  - Conference: "La couronne anglaise et l'amitié française," (held on, Jan. 27, 1939). (Box 2)
  - Conference: "La Bataille présidentielle aux Etats Unis" (Box 2)
  - Conference: "La France qui se bat," (held in USA, )., 1917? (Box 2)
  - Conference: "Souvenez-vous et espérons!" (Box 2)
  - "La Société des Nations" (Box 2)
  - Conference: "France and the World," (held at the Y.M.C.A. in, 1928). (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and notes, 1902-1951. (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks with newspaper and magazine clippings of articles authored by Stephane Lauzanne. (Box 3-11)
  - Vol. I. Articles from Le Matin (Paris) from the end of 1898. (Box 3)
  - Vol. Ia. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1901-1902. (Box 3)
  - Vol. II. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1900-1902. (Box 4)
  - Vol. III. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1902-1903. (Box 4)
  - Vol. IV. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1906. (Box 5)
  - Vol. V. Articles from various journals, 1909. (Box 5)
  - Vol. VI. Articles from various journals, 1913-1917. (Box 6)
  - Vol. VII. Articles from various journals, written in America, 1917-1918. (Box 6)
  - Vol. VIII. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1920-1921. (Box 7)
  - Vol. IX. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1922-1924. (Box 7)
  - Vol. X. Articles from various periodicals, 1925-1927. (Box 8)
  - Vol. XI. Articles (in English) from Osaka Mainichi (Osaka, Japan) and articles by "Vincent Vignon", Oct. 24, 1924 to Oct. 1932. (Box 8)
  - Vol. XII. Articles from various periodicals, 1927-1930. (Box 9)
  - Vol. XIII. Articles from various periodicals, 1930-1933. (Box 9)
  - Vol. XIV. Articles from Le Matin (Paris), 1935-1938. (Box 10)
  - Vol. XV.Articles from Le Matin and other periodicals, with dates, 1938-1943. (Box 11)
  - Vol. XVI. Articles (in English) from Osaka Mainichi (Osaka, Japan) and articles by "Vincent Vignon,", dated, 1933-1940. (Box 11)
  - Vol. XVII. Articles from Le Matin, and other periodicals about the "collaboration" trial of Le Matin's editor Stephane Lauzanne, Few articles by Lauzanne, April 1943-1944, Oct. 29, 1944. 1951-1954. (Box 10)